Guide to the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation Papers 1945-1987
University of Chicago Library
Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation. Papers
1945-1987
26 linear ft. (52 box)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The records of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation comprise 26 linear feet of material, including minutes, correspondence, and financial records of the Foundation, as well as applications, recommendations, correspondence, reports, newsletters, news clippings, and pamphlets of 65 organizations that applied to the Foundation for support. The Schwarzhaupt records are important documents for studying an important shift in the understanding of democratic participation in the mid-twentieth century. In the Foundation's certificate of incorporation in 1936 Emil Schwarzhaupt wrote of: the up building and betterment of American citizenship and increasing among all American citizens, and especially among the foreign born, the knowledge of the history of the United States Government and the meaning of the obligations and privileges of citizenship in the United States of America.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation was established in New York on July 21, 1936 by Emil Schwarzhaupt, a German immigrant who came to the United States in 1910 at the age of seventeen. Schwarzhaupt first worked as a salesman for several distilling firms in Chicago. In 1927 he helped to organize the American Medicinal Spirits Company and served on its board of directors until it was purchased by the National Distillers Products Corporation in 1930, when he became director and vice president of that corporation.
In 1933 Schwarzhaupt and Leo Gerngross acquired the Bernheimer Distilling Company in Louisville, KY. Schwarzhaupt became president of the firm and remained in that position after the company was purchased by Schenly Industries, Inc. Emil Schwarzhaupt retired in 1948 and died March 30, 1950.
Schwarzhaupt's interest in promoting an intelligent understanding of American citizenship among the foreign born led him to create the Foundation that bears his name and to bequeath a substantial share of his estate to its work. The bequest in his will resulted in the sale of 113,000 shares of the Bernheimer Company to Schenly Industries for about $3.6 million.
Schwarzhaupt had no intention of making a permanent institution of the Schwarzhaupt Foundation. He stated in his will:
"…any moneys, securities, other assets or property…all be expended within the period of 25 years from and after the date of my death. My reason for imposing the restriction and conditions…because of my conviction that in the long run society is benefited by having each generation solve its own problems and provide the necessary funds for so doing."
The initial group of trustees consisted of four friends of Schwarzhaupt: Leo Gerngross (first president), Adolph Hirsch, Hugo Sonnenschein and Frederick Lee. Schwarzhaupt's will stipulated that three years after his death three additional trustees were to be added to the board, "to be selected by the then presiding head of the Catholic Archdiocese of New York, the then acting head of the Federal Council of Churches of New York, and the then acting Rabbi of Temple Emanu-el of New York City."
After the bequests specifically stipulated in his will to family, friends, and a sizeable number of public and private institutions had been disbursed, the trustees of the Foundation were unsure how to proceed with the allocation of the remainder of the funds. Schwarzhaupt, as noted earlier, had suggested in his will that the Foundation's funds could be used to distribute materials on American citizenship to immigrants, to endow a university chair devoted to the study of American citizenship. But Schwarzhaupt did not make these suggestions binding upon the trustees. Adolph Hirsch, who became president of the Foundation after Gerngross's death in 1958, commented on this lack of direction by saying that he and Gerngross had asked Schwarzhaupt for more specific guidance. Schwarzhaupt replied that "if he had known, he would have set it down."
With the purpose of the Foundation unresolved, the trustees decided to meet with Professor Louis Wirth of the University of Chicago in 1951. Wirth was a professor of sociology who was interested in problems of civic leadership and training, especially as it related to urban areas. It was decided that Wirth and others in the department would apply to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation for funds to create a committee to study the theoretical problems of education and citizenship. The Foundation provided $25,300 to establish the Committee on Education for American Citizenship. Louis Wirth became chairman, and other committee members were Daniel Boorstin, Kermit Eby, Walter Johnson, Avery Leiserson, Bessie Louise Pierce, Kenneth J. Rehage, and Ralph W. Tyler.
The final recommendations of the Committee suggested that an advisory group "representing a diversity of backgrounds" be formed to review and evaluate grant applications. Instead, the trustees hired Carl Tjerandsen on a consulting basis in 1953 to review applications submitted to the Foundation and to make recommendations based on the Foundation's statement of purpose. Tjerandsen had helped organize an "Institute on Citizenship" at Kansas State College in the mid-1940s prior to attending graduate school at the University of Chicago where he worked with Professor Louis Wirth. It was as a graduate student that he worked with the Committee on Education for American Citizenship, and after the death of Professor Wirth was appointed by Dean Ralph Tyler as Executive Secretary to the Committee. Based on his analysis of the initial applications to the Foundation, and his previous experience at Kansas State College, Tjerandsen was hired in 1953. It was Tjerandsen who essentially performed the work of the Foundation for its entire duration.
An important feature of the Committee's report was the recommendation that grant-making activities be divided among three discrete areas. The first was defined as the "improvement of citizenship participation on a community basis," the second as support for research on the "process of becoming an American citizen," and the third as funding worthwhile groups related to the Foundation's statement of purpose which did not fall under the first two categories.
The Committee developed five criteria which were adopted by the trustees in evaluating the merits of the applications: 1) Did the application fall within the established guidelines of education and citizenship participation? 2) Were the proposed activities consistent with the aims of the proposals? Did the applicants show how the activities might be expected to change citizen behavior? 3) Did the applicants have the understanding, interest, and skills to complete the project? 4) Was the program practical? Would the resources be adequate to deal with the particular situation? 5) Was the probable cost sufficiently small in relation to expected benefits to warrant the support from the foundation's modest resources?
In addition to the five criteria mentioned above, institutions and groups applying for funding from the Foundation had to meet three further requirements: they had to be tax-exempt organizations; they could not be on the U.S. Attorney General's list of subversive organizations; and they were to be engaged in either research or education to improve citizen participation.
In the course of its existence, the Schwarzhaupt Foundation disbursed $3,361,973 in grants. The kinds of projects receiving Foundation support included: cooperative nursery care in an interracial community (South Chicago Community Center); research projects to identify problems in citizenship organizations (the University of Michigan survey of the League of Women Voters); neighborhood improvement organizations (United Community Fund of San Francisco, Citizens Planning and Housing Association of Baltimore, Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference); and organizations to improve the citizen participation of minority groups (Highlander Folk School, Industrial Areas Foundation, Migrant Ministry, American Indian Development, and Unitarian Service Committee). A significant if not disproportionate number of projects from the Chicago area were funded, causing occasional concern among the board members. In fact, Saul Alinsky's Industrial Areas Foundation in Chicago received so much money from Schwarzhaupt that at least one author assumed the Schwarzhaupt Foundation was located in Chicago (see Saul Alinsky's humorous letter of April 14, 1966 in Box 29 Folder 18).
In the 1950s, during the Foundation's greatest period of activity, the trustees met twice a year, later reducing this to one meeting a year (usually held in New York). Before each meeting of the Foundation, Tjerandsen prepared a 1-3 page report on each grant application received along with recommendations for approval or denial. The trustees received these summaries in advance of the board meetings, and then came to a conclusion regarding the project.
In addition to the recommendations (or appraisals) of grant applications that Tjerandsen supplied to the trustees, he also submitted monthly reports. These reports introduced new applications received, results of meetings held with grant recipients, and summaries of reports submitted by the recipients. Then, at the board meeting, Tjerandsen summarized the appraisal and contributed to the discussion that followed. Application was not made unless it reflected a consensus. If any trustee had significant reservations about an application, the proposal was rejected.
The terms of Schwarzhaupt's bequest to the Foundation required that all funds were to be disbursed and the Foundation dissolved within 25 years of Emil Schwarzhaupt's death (March 30, 1950). Accordingly, the trustees met on March 31, 1975 to discuss a course of action. Adolph Hirsch reported that "substantially all the assets of the foundation, both principal and income, had been distributed." The trustees noted that the only project not yet completed was the writing, publication, and distribution of the final report. The trustees concluded that it was premature to adopt a plan of dissolution since activities in connection with the report would require "new contractual relations for the publication and distribution of the report."
The trustees did not meet again until April 15, 1979, when they again considered dissolution of the Foundation. Tjerandsen, who prepared the final report, explained that a draft was being written but that it would take an "extended time" before the report would be ready. The trustees decided to wait until after the report was published before considering dissolution.
The final report, Education for Citizenship: A Foundation's Experience, was published in 1980. Promotional circulars were mailed to individuals and institutions likely to benefit from the report's findings, and copies of the book were distributed without charge to those who returned a postal card.
By late 1981 about 1500 copies of a press run of about 200 had been distributed, and the trustees met in November to consider termination of the Foundation. While the actual date of dissolution is not found in the records, the trustees in their final actions granted some of the remaining funds of the Foundation to the Highlander Center, Resources for Just Communities, Santa Cruz, California, to cover the costs of distributing the final reports, and the remainder to the University of Chicago Library to process the records of the Foundation.
Scope Note
The records of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation comprise minutes, correspondence, and financial records of the Foundation, as well as applications, recommendations, correspondence, reports, newsletters, news clippings, and pamphlets of sixty-five organizations that applied to the Foundation for support.
The Schwarzhaupt records are important documents for studying a major shift in the understanding of democratic participation in the mid-twentieth century. In the Foundation's certificate of incorporation in 1936 Emil Schwarzhaupt wrote of:
the up building and betterment of American citizenship and increasing among all American citizens, and especially among the foreign born, the knowledge of the history of the United States Government and the meaning of the obligations and privileges of citizenship in the United States of America.
This idealistic conception of citizenship and the state was in contrast to the actual practice of the Foundation after 1950 in awarding grants to such organizations as Saul Alinsky's Industrial Areas Foundation, and the Highlander Folk School, which emphasized a more confrontational understanding of citizenship under the rubric of "community organizing." The career of the Schwarzhaupt Foundation thus embodied a tension between theory and practice that is reflected in the varied approaches adopted by the organizations it funded. It is the records of these diverse organizations and groups that comprise the bulk of this collection.
The records of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation have been divided into three series: Series I (Boxes 1-6) contains the administrative records of the Foundation, Series II (Boxes 6-51) contains records of the organizations having dealings with the Foundation, and Series III (Box 52) contains photographs.
Series I: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS
The first series includes general records of the Foundation relating to its administration and finances. This series is divided into ten subject headings: Organizational and Disbursement of Emil Schwarzhaupt Estate, covering activities before 1952; University of Chicago Committee on Education for American Citizenship: Recommendations; Minutes and Financial Reports; Financial Statements and Tax Returns; Correspondence covering the day-to-day activities of the Foundation; Activity Reports; Grant Application Recommendations, containing many initial recommendations written between 1954 and 1955 by Tjerandsen; Evaluation Report of Highlander Folk School and Industrial Areas Foundation, containing the correspondence and final report of J. Herman Blake, who was commissioned to study two Schwarzhaupt-Funded projects in the Sea Islands of South Carolina and in the Woodlawn neighborhood of Chicago; Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation: Final Report, containing correspondence, notes, and drafts, along with a published copy of the report, Education for Citizenship; and American Indian Background Material Gathered by Carl Tjerandsen, which includes general notes and correspondence of Tjerandsen as well as newsletters and clippings.
Series II. APPLICATIONS FOR FUNDS AND GRANTS
This series contains the applications, recommendations, correspondence and reports of 65 organizations which applied to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation for funds, listed in alphabetical order. Tjerandsen, in his book, grouped the organizations into three types depending on their program's purpose: 1) Organizations preparing aliens for citizenship as well as patriotic organizations fostering allegiance to the country; 2) groups and program promoting awareness of civil liberties, and also groups promoting electoral participation and effective functioning of political parties; and 3) groups and programs developing personal attributes such as courage and personal character considered essential to democracy, as well as groups engaged in active community organizing. Under the heading for each organization the files are arranged in the following order:
Application and Recommendations. Under this heading appear the application and proposal submitted by organizations to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation, along with the recommendations or appraisals written by Tjerandsen for the trustees. On occasion the applying organization also submitted a statement of non-profit status for tax purposes which is included here.
Correspondence. This heading contains letters, telegrams, memoranda, notes of telephone conversations, and Tjerandsen's notes of visits and conversations in the field.
Reports. This heading contains the progress, annual, and final reports made by the grant recipients to the foundation. Not all recipients were required to submit reports at the conclusion of their projects.
Newsletters. Any newsletters published by the project were passed on to the Foundation. The name of the newsletter is given first, followed by the dates of the newsletter represented in the files.
Pamphlets. This includes other published material by the grant recipients. The Foundation requested that such materials be sent on a regular basis.
Article Reprints. If the project or the Schwarzhaupt Foundation was mentioned in an article, the grantee usually passed it along to the Foundation.
News Clippings. Any publicity covering the project or the Schwarzhaupt Foundation was usually forwarded to the Foundation.
When the amount of material for an organization is small, the reports are combined with the applications and recommendations.
Of particular interest might be the files centering on two of the most significant projects funded by the Schwarzhaupt Foundation: the Industrial Areas Foundation, headed by Saul Alinsky; and the Highlander Folk School Project, whose "citizenship classes" in the South were eventually incorporated into the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, headed by Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
The range of Alinsky's IAF extended from the community organizing work in The Woodlawn Organization to one of the most successful efforts to register Mexican-Americans to vote. The IAF organized groups known as Community Service Organizations (CSO) in towns throughout California. The CSO were eventually able to register over 400,000 voters, and as their support grew, they were able to successfully confront discrimination and to demand better treatment.
Box 29 Folder 18 contains correspondence between Alinsky and the Foundation's president, Adolph Hirsch, and the Foundation's secretary, Carl Tjerandsen, from 1964 to 1968. A number of the letters deal with the Foundation's difficulty in getting Alinsky to file project reports. In one such letter from January 10, 1966, Tjerandsen sought to impress the urgency of the reports upon Alinsky by reminding him that "about one-third of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation's funds were committed to the projects sponsored or supervised by the Industrial Areas Foundation," i.e., Alinsky's organization. In addition Box 31, Folder 1 contains the following essays and reports by Alinsky: "Action to Equality of Opportunity," "Citizen Participation and Community Organization in Planning and Urban Renewal" (January 29, 1962), "Civil Rights Housing Hearing: Commission on Civil Rights" (May 5, 1959), and "Seminar on Mass Organization" (August-September, 1965).
The connection with Martin Luther King, Jr. came through the Schwarzhaupt Foundation's support of project sponsoring citizenship classes, the Highlander Folk School. Tjerandsen found this project to be the most influential and far-reaching of all the programs supported by the Foundation.
The idea of citizenship classes grew out of an application written by Myles Horton, a director of Highlander, in 1952. The Highlander project began on John's Island, near Charleston, South Carolina, under the direction of Septima
Clark and Esau Jenkins, and emphasized voter registration and civic education. As Myles Horton once put it: "What is too big for one person to handle can be figured out by all of us together. We will have a new kind of school-not a school for teaching reading, writing and arithmetic, but a school for problems."
Boxes 22-25 contain extensive material on the Highlander Folk School with important documents discussing the shift of the citizenship classes from Highlander to the SCLC. The best general discussion of the transfer of the transfer of the classes occurs in the essay, "A Workshop for Volunteer Teachers in the Citizenship Program of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, 1965" (24:15). As early as 1961, however, a "Memorandum on Citizenship Program" (24:6) emphasized the transition of the classes to the SCLC. Significant to the continuity of the program developed by the SCLC was the retention of Highlander's Director of Education, Septima Clark. By 1967, there were over three thousand citizenship teachers who had helped hundreds of thousands of blacks to register to vote. Although the Schwarzhaupt Foundation did not fund the educational efforts of the SCLC (which was supported by the Field Foundation), its work with Highlander prepared the way for the development of such a program.
Other significant projects assisted by the Schwarzhaupt Foundation include: the American Indian Conference in Chicago in 1962, which drew over 800 Indians from more than 90 tribes-the largest gathering of Indians to that point to discuss problems and concerns; the American Council for Emigres in the Professions (ACEP); the Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference; and the Migrant Citizen Education Project.
Series III. PHOTOGRAPHS
This series contains four folders of black and white photographs of activities from a number of organizations, along with color slides from an additional group. Folder 1 contains photographs emphasizing the people with whom the Highlander Project worked in the rural South. Folder 2 illustrates classroom situations of the Highlander citizenship classes. Folder 3 portrays activities and gatherings of the Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference, and other groups including Migrant Ministry. Folder 4 contains color slides of the Gallup Citizenship Education Program used in class presentations.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Tjerandsen, Carl; Alinsky, Saul David, 1909-1972; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); Industrial Areas Foundation; Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation; Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference; Migrant Citizen Education Project; South Chicago Community Center; Citizens Planning & Housing Association (Baltimore, Md.); American Indian Development Associates; Political participation-United States; Political socialization-United States; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations-United States; Citizenship-United States
INVENTORY
- Series I: Administrative Records
  - Subseries 1: Organization and Disbursement of Emil Schwarzhaupt Estate
    - Emil Schwarzhaupt Last Will and Testament, December 19, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation, Certificate of Report of Existence, March 7, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Acknowledgements of bequests received from the Emil Schwarzhaupt estate; 1950-1951, American Friends Service Committee-Beth Israel Hospital (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Acknowledgements of bequests received from the Emil Schwarzhaupt estate; 1950-1951, Boy's Club of New York-Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Acknowledgements of bequests received from the Emil Schwarzhaupt estate; 1950-1951, Federation of the Handicapped-National Society for the Prevention of Blindness (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Acknowledgements of bequests received from the Emil Schwarzhaupt estate; 1950-1951, New York Adult Education Council-Volunteers of America (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: University of Chicago Committee on Education for American Citizenship; Recommendations
    - "Preliminary Recommendations to the Trustees of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation," November 8, 1952; Notes from "The Problem of Education for Citizenship" by Leonard Gardner, University of Chicago, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "An Appraisal of Certain Proposals Received by the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation," November 14, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Recommendations to the Trustees of the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation" [Draft], April 27, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)